<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ravi RT Merugu</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://rrmerugu.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://rrmerugu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 23:30:38 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 23:30:38 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mistakes I don&#39;t want to repeat in my next venture</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been an awesome experience working with Feazt for almost 1 year now. Although I’m happy about working with the company for first 6 months, I started to see the company in a different way after that. The CEO of the company phoned me when I was working in IIT Delhi and we scheduled a call for 1 hour, but the call went for nearly 3 hours, because I liked the passion of that guy. So within a week, I just informed the Professor I was working with that I’m moving to Hyderabad. Thank god I got this offer, when I just finished a project in IITD, So I didn’t hesitate to leave, but I partially still feel like I dumped a Scientist at IITD for a CTO position in Startup. But I don’t regret my decision though, I happily moved to Hyderabad with dreams and plans of becoming CTO and cofounder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don’t regret the decision of leaving IITD to work at the company, But I’m kind of unhappy that things didn’t work as expected. I’m still ok with everything, because you cannot expect startup to work in predictive mode. You may think that everything works/working in the way you want but it might not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its a very great company to work with awesome concept, passionate CEO, i wouldn’t say awesome team, but the org do have a good team and great hosts and guests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
I learned a lot things, I didn&#39;t learn anything about how exactly things work, but I understood how things don&#39;t work and why things fail.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me put some of the Learnings&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give promises wisely&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take internal meetings very seriously&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never break the trust of a team member&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are at higher position in team&lt;/strong&gt; - be more disciplined than anyone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put entire plan into paper and design a plan to execute and track&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep an eye on opponents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have an hour of product &amp;amp; company state with team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t start blaming others&lt;/strong&gt; , that you are waiting for them to initiate something.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company Fit&lt;/strong&gt; If a member is not fitting into company, don’t expect people to change for the company, just cut that member from the team. I don’t believe in giving too many chances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s me write how I felt in various situations of the journey in the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like every other guy with big dreams, I started my first day in the office, meeting new people, awesome office for a startup. This is my first time working in a IT company. CEO talked about the aspirations, culture, future plans, expectations from me, and everything. I loved the way he cared about the work culture, the team he wanted to create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week after I started working at the company, we planned a release which revamps the entire product design. I was Development &amp;amp; Technology Head, leading the project with a team of 2 frontend developers, 1 Bussines analyst cum Manual Tester and a full stack developer along with me. We fired one of the front developer, whom we thought will lead the frontend, we realized he is not a good fit. After a while we hired an intern, who is smart, fast and awesome at creating the UI. Somehow we managed to finish the release 3 months after in between which we postponed it twice. The whole reason for the failure are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;poor estimation,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;poor sprint planning,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;poor understanding of the product,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;poor source code management,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not setting the coding styles before project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learnings-from-project-management&quot;&gt;Learnings from Project Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main flaw from my side is poor code management, because I was always busy coding the things some one missed/failed to do properly. Honestly I don’t love managing people or people at all, I love coding too much that I forget everything when I do code. Although CEO wanted me to take care of the development + backend development, I did backend development with partially monitoring the codes. All the other members of the development except me and an intern are left in the team. Fortunately, we found a front end developer.  After the release, I looked at the code and felt lot of code standardization is needed, and started another project with standardizing for 1 more month. and after that CEO felt the design is not speaking the language which user can understand easily. So CEO asked designer to revamp the complete design, and she took 1 month and came with half of the product designs and the CEO wanted the development to be Agile, converting one by one of the pages to complete design change. From this moment, I lost the control over the development and I started to work completely as a developer , because I had to. I think I should refrain from getting too much into coding and focus more on over all project. Also too many revamps ruin the progress of the product, we have been designing same features from last 1 year because,  we started with something and we didnt like it again and we changed it again and again. Too many iterations will kill the spirit of the team and product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learnings-from-conducting-hiring&quot;&gt;Learnings from conducting Hiring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After most of the developers at the company left, we tried outsourcing part of the product in upwork.com. We tried hiree.com which was mynoticeperiod.com back then, I make a deal with hackerearth.com, which was not closed by CEO at the end. I dealt with hackerearth guys and negotiated a deal that was accepted by CEO and was not closed after a week with doubt of what if this doesn’t work out. But I felt so humiliated at that moment, because the business development guy from hackerearth mailed me that he wanted to revise the deal taking the deal to a costly affair, because the company is dragging the scene for too long even after deal is finalized and papers are sent to sign and make the contract. We still have no testing guy or testing role, at this point, im taking care of the full stack development + devops and other guy takes care of front end. All I realized was we should plan what we want at what cost before talking to these guys, or we will make fool of ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://rrmerugu.github.io/thoughts/team/experience/2016/02/25/mistakes-i-dont-want-to-repeat-in-my-next-venture.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rrmerugu.github.io/thoughts/team/experience/2016/02/25/mistakes-i-dont-want-to-repeat-in-my-next-venture.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Thoughts</category>
        
        <category>Team</category>
        
        <category>Experience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Eight factors of great startups</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;These are the eight factors I think I should keep in mind to build my startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Funding Ecosystem &amp;amp; Exits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engineering Talent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Active Mentoring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical Infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Startup Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Legal &amp;amp; Policy Infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Economic Foundation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Government Policies &amp;amp; Programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@bernardmoon/the-10-hottest-startup-ecosystems-in-the-world-974d0052e244#.t4ux5ms92&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://rrmerugu.github.io/startup/2016/01/02/eight-factors-of-great-startup.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rrmerugu.github.io/startup/2016/01/02/eight-factors-of-great-startup.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>startup</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Websites built on Django and their techstack </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Thinking of doing something else other than coding, I ended up understanding the technical stacks and architecture of the websites built using Django. These websites made my life much easier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackshare.io/&quot;&gt;http://stackshare.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://builtwith.com/&quot;&gt;http://builtwith.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instagram&quot;&gt;1. Instagram&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets start with Instagram, it is built using Django, its stack is discussed here &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackshare.io/instagram/instagram&quot;&gt;http://stackshare.io/instagram/instagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://instagram-engineering.tumblr.com/post/13649370142/what-powers-instagram-hundreds-of-instances&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://rrmerugu.github.io/understanding/techstack/2016/01/02/website-built-on-django-and-how.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rrmerugu.github.io/understanding/techstack/2016/01/02/website-built-on-django-and-how.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Understanding</category>
        
        <category>techstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learnings from 2015</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;These are more of learnings from different experiences  rather than mistakes in 2015. I’m sure I can do much better than what I’ve done in this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better decision making.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be serious about &lt;strong&gt;The Time&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a motive&lt;/strong&gt; for every move.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make better and more &lt;strong&gt;realistic Business Plan&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socialize&lt;/strong&gt; with people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://rrmerugu.github.io/learnings/personal/2015/12/28/learnings-from-2015.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rrmerugu.github.io/learnings/personal/2015/12/28/learnings-from-2015.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>learnings</category>
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to my First Jekyll Blog!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Blogging isn’t my thing, and I never imagined setting up a blog using Jekyll. Recently starting the new blog with Jekyll and loving it .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could be able to setup this blog in 4 hours :D Just amazing. I wasted an hour  in these 4 hrs just because I didn’t realize that changes in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; will be not reload automatically like the way it happens for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scss, css, html, md&lt;/code&gt; files. My bad I’m expecting the changed to reflect without restarting the Jekyll server. But anyways here we go, finally I’m able create a Jekyll blog starting from creating &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll new myblog&lt;/code&gt; to customising(the current state of my blog ) in just 4 hours. How cool is that :D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best things about Jekyll:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loads really fast&lt;/strong&gt; - no server side rendering anyways&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;secure&lt;/strong&gt; - no server side calculations or executions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;no database&lt;/strong&gt; - no mysql, username, password, administrations etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;markdown&lt;/strong&gt; - much better way of writing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2015 22:54:36 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://rrmerugu.github.io/welcome/jekyll/2015/12/27/welcome-to-my-first-jekyll-blog.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rrmerugu.github.io/welcome/jekyll/2015/12/27/welcome-to-my-first-jekyll-blog.html</guid>
        
        <category>ravi</category>
        
        <category>raja</category>
        
        
        <category>Welcome</category>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
